all right hello and welcome it's May
24th 2024 we're in ACM live stream
number
57.0 doing background and context video
for the active data selection and
information seeking paper and Series so
welcome to the ACM Institute we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference this is a
recorded and archive live stream please
provide feedback so we can improve our
work all backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome and we'll follow video
etiquette for live streams head over to
active inference dorg to learn more
about any of the projects including the
live
streams So today we're going
to do together a background first pass
on a very interesting paper from Thomas
par Carl friston and Peter zidan active
data selection and information seeking
from
2024 in this video we're going to
introduce ourselves talk about big
questions go through the keywords of the
paper then most of the sections section
by section and as always with the zero
it's just like a first pass and we'll
look forward to speaking with hopefully
some of the authors in the coming weeks
and also looking what people ask about
so Christopher let introduce ourself and
go from there thanks a lot also for
helping in thezero
preparation happily um yeah so I'm
Christopher Bennett I'm a bioinformatic
scientist I do a lot of uh data mangling
data analysis and that sort of thing um
this paper was of great interest to me
as we kind of go into this more data
driven era uh in making sure that with
such large data sets that we have making
sure that we can actually select data
for any of our applications going
forward be it machine learning or some
whatever we're trying to
do and I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and also was drawn to this on
one hand on the applied side the idea of
more efficient and effective data
sampling and then on the more theory
side the connection with epistemic value
Information Gain
so here are some of the big questions
why don't you add some detail to
this absolutely there was five major big
questions that I had after reading this
um for the most part it boils down
to doing our sampling you can do
sampling over time and sampling of
different data sets in different ways um
is there a way that we can um
intelligently select the data that that
we're uh going for the time that uh the
time that we're trying to select um is
there a way that we can understand how
the time aspect how to sample through
time instead of just doing a like a
dynamic uh or more Dynamic instead of
doing a static like we're going to do
Time Zero time 7 time 14 time 21 can we
say hey the differences between time one
and time two are very time point one and
time point two are very interesting
that's a lot of data in there alone so
we'll sample one and two or and then
maybe sample 10 is there a way that we
can intelligently select the time points
that we are sampling from when we get
into the time series
aspect um there's a number the piper
mentioned a number of different uh time
Dimension models that you can add to the
core model that they're utilizing um one
of which was a hidden Markov model
another was they mentioned a
differential equation in the actual uh
model itself in the equation itself um
is there
one there are there situations that one
performs better over than the other um
or is what they have selected to use in
the paper the optimal solution in most
cases if not all
cases um you know that in when it comes
to clinical trials that was a section um
in this uh that they discussed um
there's a lot of FDA uh regulations of
clinical trials and it's very uh heavy
red tape right now um is there a way
that there minimums ends that you need
in many uh clinical trials to actually
be considered passing is there a way
that you can bound this uh model that
they're they've developed in to
something that you can guarantee a
minimum number a minimum sampling that
the FDA requires or any regulatory
body um another point is the next step
of how are we going to integrate this in
with other machine learning models or
any Downstream applications that you're
going with is there a selection method
that we can uh or how do you see these
this method kind of
pre kind of before machine learning how
are we going to attach these things
together so that we feed the right data
into the machine ma
learning um being an
llm uh and then scalability and
computational demands that's going to be
a big one if this is going to be
something that is used routinely in
Industry you need to make sure that this
is something that is as in as scalable
as you can get um you know go from small
scale which is a lot of what they show
in this paper and then all the way up to
the very large scale data sets that we
use to train llms and other other models
those are kind of the five major points
that I add
here thank you those are very
insightful here were some of the big
questions that I was excited about so
first from a more General Information
Gain epistemic foraging perspective how
do we model the implicit and explicit
constraints or trade-offs or dynamics of
information seeking which is often
addressing a question that is left
unaddressed in data science of where the
data comes from and it's just about
doing analysis with the data that's
there but even there as this paper will
kind of get into there's still
subsampling and all these other factors
to
consider um the clinical trial example
brings a very serious and very real plot
twist into the paper which moves through
several levels of adding theoretical
generalization and incorporating like
the time Dimension and other features
and then the plot is when the
preferences for certain kinds of
observations is
specified then there's all this
interesting behavior and decisions that
come into play so I'm sure that'll be a
great discussion and then also in
section four they mention the
streetlight effect which is quote the
tendency to search where data are
generated in a minimally ambiguous way
I.E under a Street Lamp compared to
searching Elsewhere on a darken Street
and so there it's an interesting
scenario and there'll be some fun art
coming up and also how they distinguish
the sampling method with the full
information seeking from the maximum
entropy sampling is a very subtle but
very important point that I look forward
to hearing more from the authors
[Music]
about okay so just
to summarize the uh paper is active data
selection and information seeking 20 24
Thomas par Carl friston Peter idman and
just a few of the aims and claims of the
paper and then Christopher will read the
abstract this paper aims to unpack the
principles of active sampling of data by
drawing from neurobiological research on
Animal Exploration and from the theory
of optimal experimental design our
overall aim is to provide an intuitive
overview of the principles that
underwrite active data selection and to
illustrate this with some simple
examples our interest is in the
selection of data either through
sampling subsets of data from a large
data set or through optimizing
experimental design based upon the
models we have of how those data are
generated optimizing data selection
ensures we can achieve good inference
with fewer data saving on computational
and and experimental costs so if you
could read the
abstract absolutely so the main uh
points in the abstract are um that
basing inference is is typically focused
on two major issues uh the first one is
that you have to estimate the parameters
of the model of the data and the second
is that you need to quantify the
evidence for alternative hypotheses uh
and formulate an alternative model um
but this paper is actually looking at a
third issue which is in how you're going
to select the data for your models um
and either through sampling subsets of
large data is typically used um or
optimizing ter of design um based upon
the models we have have these of how
these data are generated um optimizing
data selection what's going into the
models can achieve a very good um
inference with fewer data points so
you're saving on computational time
costs that sort of thing by actually
reducing the amount of information that
you're putting into the
model so what they're doing here is
trying to unpack how you're going to AC
L select data and I mean actively select
data to a machine um optimization
protocol by drawing from some of these
neurobiology Concepts um and trying to
optimize the maximum information that a
that the information can provide maximum
Information Gain um so they offer
overview of some basic points uh from
these from the field and illustrates the
application in some of the toy examples
that they have will go through ranging
from different approximations uh with
basis sets uh to infant about how the
process can evolve over
time and finally they'll go through and
consider how the approach to the data
selection could be applied to design of
uh clinical trials in this case and uh
specifically Bas adapted clinical trial
something that is more and more uh
seeing headlines and kind of it's more
and more used today now that we have the
technology to do
with great okay for the road map the
paper begins with introduction section
goes into basian inference generative
models and expected Information Gain
they go through a simplest worked
example and then consider a few more
ways to level up that model with
function
approximation consideration of time
Dimension with Dynamic processes and
then bringing the preference for certain
observations in the clinical trials then
there's a discussion and conclusion and
they also have a paragraph explaining
their kind of logic there the keywords
for the paper were experimental design
active sampling Information Gain and
basian inference so the next slides are
going to go into those four background
topics after the four background topics
we'll speed through the sections and
just plant a few seeds for what we want
want to explore more so first
experimental design here's two kind of
classical views of experimental design
in the active inference and free energy
principle uh eras so on the left is the
statistical parametric mapping textbook
toolbox documentation Etc has multiple
chapters and kinds of analyses included
in the package to specify and simulate
and also to recognize data according to
different experimental designs and one
very Hallmark or common visualization of
these kinds of patterns of experimental
design are these design matrices and
it's just represented in this black to
white gray scale and it summarizes
different kinds of measurements across
different experimental settings like
here might be six settings in the larger
white blocks and then there was
variability within each of those trials
and those are the smaller row levels so
that's like where the data are collected
and a lot of this has to do with the
linear operations that can occur on this
kind of Matrix in a general linear
modeling framework and then on the right
is the experimental design experimenters
perspective where the experimental
stimuli they output as actions are the
observations going into the subjective
model like of the rat in the teamas and
then the action output of the Rat is the
observations of the experiment of the
experimenter so there are kind of two
different perspectives SPM with more of
a matrix
multiplication
fmri optimal design and then active
inference with a more General graphical
basian modeling starting to broaden the
consideration of what optimal foraging
and what Information Gain epistemic
value mean these are kind of the
experiment design themes and how they
connect a little bit with other
experimental design factors want to add
anything yeah and keep in mind that a
lot of these experiments experimental
design is a very big um and Mo and very
important consideration when you're
actually running any sort of science or
analytics of any variety and these
experiments can actually get very large
with huge huge amounts of data and not
all of that data is relevant for every
application that you want so you want to
be able to design your experiments in a
way that you can collect information in
a intelligent way rather than trying to
go through and just collect every data
point that you can because humans in
many cases are running some of these
experiments and they have limited time
um I certainly do when I'm running these
things so I have to be very intelligent
in how I set things up and how I
actually collect data and what data I
collect because you only get in many of
these cases you only get one shot to
collect the data if you miss it it's
over you won't have that data point so
it it's very critical that you actually
take the experimental design seriously
when you're setting these things
up great so connecting that kind of
experimental design experiment on a
budget perspective with a more
statistical and
biologically statistical based uh
perspective active sample so they wrote
when we look at the world around us we
are implicitly engaging in a form of
active data sampling also known as
active sensing or active inference so
this is referencing the visual Cades and
just to kind of highlight how extreme
the relative Acuity difference is
between the center of the eye where the
Gaze is focused on and the offc center
among other visual changes and vision is
just being taken as one sensory example
here it could also be thought of as like
looking for books within a library or
any other kind of selection of what data
are going to come in even if it seems
like all of it is coming in that still
is going to be uh perhaps addressed with
a different sensors that have different
variability profiles or like there's
different RNA sequencing kits that you
could buy and so how do you balance the
kind of more samples or Wich samples
especially as those spaces grow massive
and then just to contrast that whereas
digit recognition in a cade based
Paradigm would focus on the motor
patterns and the small centrally focused
visual Acuity and then the motor
patterns that relate to cating around a
digit whereas in the kind of machine
learning taken all at once approach a
matrix corresponding to like the pixels
in the mnist data set are simply taken
in all at equivariant
level so that's just kind of taking in
the data there's still is another higher
order data selection question of like
which digits do you take if there was a
large number of digits in that Library
so this is uh active data sampling on
multiple scales which records you pull
at all and then how the resolution and
all the trade-offs that are associated
with using the data processing or making
the experiment yeah add more
though and you know keep in mind that in
the when you're talking about something
like the visual system you know our
visual system has access to untold
amounts of information but our brain
can't take advantage of all of that at
once there low energy usage of the brain
it needs to optimize the relevant
information think you know your nose is
right at the end of your face your eyes
are always seeing your nose but your
brain is filtering it out and this is
happening all the time at all points in
time there are literal blind spots in
what you are actually capable of
intaking and processing all at once uh
and then additionally when you're moving
away from something like your the ey or
biological systems and into the
experiment design itself you know you
often times can't run a full factorial
design and there are other methods like
a fractional factorial design but those
are random based and this is trying to
actually talk about actively selecting
how you're going to set up that design
so it's kind of a a you can think of it
in multiple different
ways awesome the factor that's going to
come into play as driving the active
sampling is going to be the information
gain and there's some quotes here and
equation two is
shown they write we have conditioned our
model upon the variable Pi which
represents a choice we can make in
selecting our data so data recognition
interpretation analysis and so on it's
often framed as kind of like an
observation type or sensemaking type
activity here Pi for policy as with
usual is Being Framed as a control or an
active data selection policy we're
applying to some data set so it adds a
action element into this sequential
epistemic foraging rather than just
taking a large data set and just
munching it like all at once it brings
in this sequential question of where to
sample
and potentially updating where is
informative to sample through time and
the if of Pi is the functional on that
policy distribution or specific choice
that can be decomposed all these
interesting ways that we can explore
more in the coming discussions what else
would you add though about Information
Gain I think this is one of the biggest
points in this whole paper is you're
measuring how much information you are
gaining in your model by adding these
different Vari Ables in here and
selecting different variables you're
effectively automatically taking out or
trying to remove things that have high
Mutual information that don't add as
much so if you have parameter a and
parameter B that are effectively just
transformations of the same data then
you can easily remove one of those and
still have all the information that you
need um so it's a really really powerful
way of saying I'm trying to optimize and
maximize the amount of information that
I'm adding in into the model by
selecting data that actually has the
information that is going to improve the
model awesome one other interesting
angle here is often in the control
literature utility reinforcement
learning Etc the epistemic value
component is added in whereas in the
structure of this paper they start with
the pure Information Gain perspective
and then in the clinical trial they
bring the preference in so the pragmatic
value comes in secondary to the
information gain in how they build it up
step by
step um basing inference is the last
keyword a lot of places to go here's
what they showed for equation
one and they wrote basian inference is
the process of inverting a a model of
how data y are generated to obtain two
things the marginal likelihood and the
posterior probability
so anything you want to say about basan
inference or do you want to say
something about basian networks and
graphs I think that you've kind of
covered it here it's I think fairly
textbook on this part yeah how about
graphs on the basian graph side of it um
there's multiple different ways that
these basian statistics is done nowadays
and the basing networks and graphs is is
a really powerful method going forward
um I know that uh right now in The
Institute we have an RX and fur uh group
working right now which is a Julia
package for actually building these
Network graphs these basian graphs and
doing message passing between the
different factors and the different
nodes of the graph so this is a a very
big upand cominging area right now it's
it's very early in the um in the time
frame that this is going to become big
it's kind of on the upswing right now um
and it it's kind of at least I would
predict GNA be kind of the next big
thing going forward uh in the next five
years or
so yeah we've been having a great
epistemic time and live stream 55
explores some of this in more
detail okay that was the background now
on to the
paper so first just to get the last part
of the paper out of the way they have a
GitHub Thomas pars GitHub with the
active data selection repo and maybe in
one of the upcoming discussions or
somebody in the time between can explore
and and transform and play with the code
and also all these different ways that
we we have fun discussions around the
language of the active influence model
and how building it in different
languages or using different styles like
is or isn't plausible these have been
very fun discussions that that help us
get out what the core of the math really
is and how that's independent of whether
it's written in mat lab or any other
language and then also as it is
simulated it's written here in Matt lab
and so that's kind of interesting any
thoughts on that or just like coding in
RX and fur or
or yeah I think that with ARX and fur
being I think relatively new on the
scene you have some of these other
traditional uh approaches with mat lab
and pimd and that sort of thing um it'll
be very interesting to see how these
techniques uh evolve over time with
packages like RX and fur um really I
think changing how we approach building
these models and designning them I think
that it's going to be even more critical
now um in this current environment to
select the data intelligently going in
so that you're not muddying up your
models or having to build to Big of
models that might have information
that's not as useful to the application
at
hand yeah great all right section one
introduction so we'll try to hit on some
of the key points I'll say something
briefly and then feel free to add
something if you want section one
situates that inference an action cycle
or Loop or partition in terms of a
statistician's job or process in
modeling observations data as sampled
and latent variables as models and the
process by which there's kind of
snapshot or bulk summarization or
generativity or and how it's possible to
have a continuous resample sampling of
informative data or how you even
evaluate how data are informative in
which
way want to add anything I think you've
captured that very well I'm GNA actually
pull out my notes so that I can actually
uh remember all the
symbols y are going to be used for data
and Theta for the latent variabl so
distributions of data distributions of
latent variables conditioned upon data
coming in so that could be seen as just
one data point sequentially or a big
bulk Vector coming in like all at
once um just continuing to move through
this section they wrote careful data
selection is especially important when
we consider the problems associated with
very large data sets of the sort that
are now ubiquitous in machine learning
and artificial intelligence
settings so just to summarize a little
bit or add a few notes that came up in
the paper so other than this topic being
very fascinating and very integrative in
terms of a unifying approach for
information Behavior Etc also this is
definitely one of the active inference
questions that has a lot of pragmatic
relevance as dealing with with data sets
of different kind is totally day-to-day
and especially the way that even the
examples specify important settings is
very clear very direct though also the
mathematics are very general about
epistemics and this motivation that they
lay out in the first section about how
if this challenge could be addressed
then there would be all these kinds of
benefits that could be realized with
current systems and data sets and then
they provide the approach to at least
getting there or towards it to optimize
data selection we first need to identify
an appropriate optimality Criterion and
so they're going to kind of go through
several stages of with different
generative
models how that optimality Criterion is
defined anything else T and keep in mind
that this is the expected Information
Gain that they're talking about it's
effectively how much do we think we're
going to gain by adding this information
in there and then you can of course
train your model by looking at the
actual Information Gain if necessary and
go through kind of a learning cycle but
we're basing this all off of what do we
expect to gain from this
information all right section two
phasing inference generative models and
expected Information
Gain in this equation three I won't read
it all it models the marov blanket
formalism in terms of upstream and
downstream causal
relationships in terms of messages that
are passed along edges of a factor
graph that they introduce in this paper
the Lambda operator to indicate either
summation or integration so this is
across continuous variables or discrete
variables and we'll explore this more
with the authors hopefully anything you
want to add on equation
three uh more that you know the
information um gain is a function of the
data that you sample so depending on how
you sample that data you're going to get
different information gained out of it
as you would expect um and then you
start to get into the message passing
which is that base graph and Factor
graph um I guess challenge going forward
that that construct when you build it in
a factor graph model you have to be able
to pass the messages between the nodes
effectively yeah and to to kind of
ground that in the data science
situation if you have a latent State
estimate and you're generating data
generative AI synthetic data then the
latent variable is Upstream causally
statistically from the data pseudo
observation but that might be the actual
real observation if you're interested in
the computer model whereas the data
recognition case where the data are
Upstream of the estimate of a parameter
like a risk score or something like that
then the parent of the lat and state
estimate is the data so that's the
recognition Direction so this kind of
covers the whole basian update
possibility Spectrum in this essentially
markof blanket but it could be in face
base or time or a few other situations
that
explore all right three a worked
example this section lays out the
overall pipeline for how you get from
the graphical notation of the basian
network whether it's viewed visually
graphically like with a variable
dependency structure or whether it's
just written out in terms of the plain
text with the analytical the bayy
network is transformed into a factor
graph probably constraint Factor graph
discussion for another day on that graph
certain messages are passed at inference
runtime conditional and predictive
entropies are calculated as part of the
way that this system outputs or is
described by different probability
distributions understand in a kind of
statistical mechanical way in terms of
entropy and then that is going to come
together into calculation of the
objective function which is the expected
Information Gain which is basically
conditioned upon the cognitive model of
the sampler so just because the sampling
is active data sampling
doesn't mean that it's going to lead to
like an
Adaptive Behavior it just means that
where the learning rate is perceived to
be highest informationally
iteratively there is a ranking by which
those can be uh which this the space of
experiments can be ranked by and it can
connect to pragmatic value in terms of e
epistemic and pragmatic coming together
for the full expected free energy like
in the clinical trial anything dad and
you'll notice in for this story example
uh that they are discussing here um the
factors that they have in their graph in
each of their uh nodes is actually a
cosign so that's why you get that kind
of oscillation in that bottom plot there
um so you'll have uh areas of maximal uh
information and then areas of minimal
information just based on the Tog EX
example they have um and this doesn't
always have to be cosine but in this
example it is and so it just kind of
gives you a really good graphical
understanding of how your Information
Gain uh can be viewed over a sinusoidal
sort of
oscillation yeah just to kind of double
down that if you sample right here on
the number line or right here the lines
are indistinguishable so the Information
Gain Is expected to be low under
understanding the parameter family that
is being generated and sampled from
which in this first example is the same
same type of equations whereas where the
functions are maximally distinct The
Information Gain associated with
reducing uncertainty about which one of
those five the the data point is coming
from those are the informative points at
the zero on the number line and far out
that's where just perceiving one point
uncolored would give you the most
ability to even perfectly resolve which
one of the five situations it
was so oh they right in effect this
model amplifies or attenuates the
amplitude of the predicted data
depending upon a periodic function of
our data sampling policy Pi so here the
the policy distribution is like that
kind of Around the Clock Direction which
is not a common setting but the the
general idea of sampling amongst a
finite set of
Alternatives where a control variable is
going to result in the most
informative data point is a theme that
is going to be expanded upon and also uh
one interesting mathematical move once
all terms that are constant with respect
to Pi are eliminated we are left with
equation six so equation five comes down
to equation six or maybe not exactly
only 5 six but six has removed all the
the
the variables that don't change as
policy changes so if the question of
policy selection is taken alone like
gradients on policy updating then
everything that's constant with respect
to it doesn't come into like the Delta
Pi Delta something so it just simplifies
it down to only a function of policy and
that just kind of reflects how like the
Sens making and belief updating
component is partitioned off from the
policy selection component
here yeah you're looking for change in
um your belief based on the observations
that you're gained so if it's not
changing it's not as informative in your
information model
yeah uh continuing on equation six there
which is modeling the policy dependent
components of Information Gain as an
objective function that ranks decisions
about where to
sample uh equation six is a special case
of the third row of table one which
highlights analytical expressions for
expected Information Gain for a few
common model
structures as we might in it the most
informative places the sample data
aligned with those in which differences
in data lead to large differences in the
predicted data in which our choice of Pi
maximizes the sensitivity with which why
depends on data so here are the the
categorical the darish
lay uh and other functions in terms of
how they'd be written out in the
probabilistic like specifying a
distribution way and then how there's
this relationship and analytically to a
related
distribution which is an objective
function that ranks the information
content of sampling the likelihood
distribution in a certain way and that's
closed form in certain situations and
then also the Explorer where it's
intractable formally and so then that's
where the variational approximation
comes into play anything to add no I
think that Su summarizes this slide okay
section four function
approximation we next turn to a generic
supervised learning problem that of
trying to approximate some function
based upon known inputs and the
observable outcomes they stochastically
cause pretty
General neural network or latent State
observation
setup um
that information is composed and
concatenated so so that there's a a
common variable with that that's
describing the statistical object that's
going to be describing the inputs and
the relationship with the observable
outcomes and then
that uh function
approximation from sequential data in
figure 3 is simulated with
random but potentially you could call
all of them random but this one is a a
flatter
or uh a a less informed and iterated
model of data sampling just going to
show that uh samples of random data with
even this minimal non Information Gain
driven model has a certain Baseline
prediction that's associated with
certain choices about sampling
sequentially from this generative
model want to add anything yeah it's
just I like that they highlighted in
this uh that choice diagram there that
um you can actually get the inefficient
sampling just by random that you start
to Rand you can randomly select two
things very close together um and you've
effectively maybe not wasted a choice
but you know not gotten the maximum gain
from that choice that you could have
have
yeah they write a little bit more about
figure
three figure 3 illustrates a depiction
of this model as a basy network and a
visual representation of the data
generating
process um now they're going to bring in
Information Gain so they write this is
where Information Gain becomes relevant
into designing a a more informed way to
sample data then from a flat or a
non-updating prior data sampling
distribution it's like equivalent to
having a policy prior that's fixed which
might be a heris in certain
space um they write substitute
substituting equation 7 into equation
three so here's
that um Markov blanket parent child
concept and here equation three is
describing the policy dependence on The
Joint distribution of The observed and
the
unobserved and this is combined into
equation
10 to show what equation 10 does in
terms of now that we're sampling from
this distribution or like statistical
distributions that this describes um
they'll differentiate figure three from
figure four kind of like bring in this
model change between those two figures
now samples are drawn from a
distribution whose log is proportional
to the information gain in equation 10
so it takes the flat policy prior and in
a fixed way has remapped it to be
proportional to the information gain so
here's three on the right and then four
on the right and um the figure uses the
same format as figure three but now each
choice is sampled to maximize
anticipated Information Gain and they
point to some specific uh quantitative
patterns but also like qualitative
patterns so want to add anything on
figure four just that now if you focus
on those choices because that I really
didn't I think like that choice plot
there you can see that the walks around
kind of choices around your data space
are a little bit more uh distributed
evenly distributed a little bit less
random but you start to get I think a
more cohesive sampling of the data
without entire range this putting things
too close together putting selections
too close
together
yeah okay continuing on uh well they set
up the question as this raises the
question as to how many samples should
we collect So within a foraging bout
where should one look and then at the
kind of like pulling a layer back in the
strategy when should you halt looking
like if you have already sampled all
three records from a data set
then unless you had some other reason
you could fully stop sampling there but
you also what might want to have a
softer stopping Criterion that would
relate to how much information you're
gaining from continuing to sample in
that way before like halting and so they
include that by having like an exit
policy in the state space of foraging
possibilities um so how do you resolve
that an answer to this question can be
drawn from behavioral neuroscience in
the so-called exploitation exploration
dilemma um and they introduced the
notion of sampling costs to help decide
that so this method is still going to
require
parameterization and situation specific
modeling of the relative costs versus
the relative Information Gain however at
least there's an accounting that
includes costs into the sampling
equation to give any possibility of
exiting because if no costs are provided
for sampling then the model might just
converge and continue to eek out very
small amounts of variance explained um
if it doesn't explicitly have that stop
option so they take the policy uh Vector
the the list of locations that can be
sampled from and adds a zero element
which reflects the information gained if
we were to stop
sampling and then there's a preference
over those observations
Express in the C Vector
preferences and this brings in the
information seeking and the cost of vers
of imperatives into the same objective
function in 11 anything to add on 11
yeah eventually the idea is that it just
gets to a point where you're no longer
whatever you set your kind of stopping
like energy to be um kind of you're
breaking energy eventually it's just
going to get to a point where the model
just says Hey I've reached what I can
you've set this you're not gaining any
anything beyond this point we can just
stop at this point which is nice since
in the random selection case there not
necessarily a stopping parameter as
Daniel mentioned you could continue to
get eek out very very small marginal
changes um but you're not going to gain
anything else and so you're just
spinning your wheels for no reason so
this is a very elegant way of saying hey
I've reached kind of an inflection point
of data gain
I'm
done so figure five they're continuing
in this genre of
345 and now they've added in to the
policy
decision which which has an upstream
dependency on the data that's the active
policy
Edge they add in
this uh cost to sampling so we can
explore more however it now includes not
just the Information Gain driven choices
within the trial But it includes a a
specific probabilistic but decisive
stopping point for that trial as
parameterized by how sensitive it is to
Information Gain and
preference so this is one of the most
interesting parts and and discussions in
the paper they they ask it out loud a
reasonable question to ask at this stage
is why bother with the full information
seeking objective and basically how does
this differ from Maximum entropy
sampling and
um let's look forward to the authors or
other guests but here's just a few notes
on this because I think it'll be a great
place to explore what it really means to
do uh statistical and physical modeling
on cognitive
systems they directly contrast maximum
entropy sampling
and their whole Information Gain uh
family against each other and then the
rebuttal is in figure six so just to
show figure six for a
second the measurement noise increases
in variance from the center of the
function domain so the the the
variability profile of the function is
nonuniform this me this means the amount
of unresolvable uncertainty is
heterogenous through the domain of
potential sampl
so I in some kind of ways of thinking
about what they're really getting at and
just putting this out as a a speculation
or starting point for for this key
technical point so if there were a case
where the latent states were equivariant
they had IID variability profiles then
sampling the most variable sensory data
is the most informative like if you're
taking a picture of a solid black image
then sampling from the noisy pixels is
going to potentially provide more
information gain you're reducing your
uncertainty more about something you
might be overfitting but you can select
as a heris wanting to sample from where
variability is high at just kind of a
first past
layer however as we start to think about
richer or more specified
statistical patterns generative models
there become
dependencies that are sparse but
important amongst all different kinds of
things so things that are variable from
a sensory
perspective provide High Information
Gain potentially to one part of a
generative model like um a screen and
static but then
other events might be less variable from
a sensory perspective Ive but smaller
differences even in that variable relate
to some other component of uncertainty
resolution from some other component of
the the model like those are going to be
the cases where cognitive modeling does
differ from just dispersed decision
making however they're both going to
result in dispersed decisionmaking
profiles like looking at the choices in
um the
figures but the choices to sample from
the less ambiguous parts of the actual
distribution that leads to a much
narrower policy path in this cognitive
control
setting versus in a variability
sampling where it would go for the areas
that were just more variable but not
necessarily providing more
information question mark
add on this with the maximum entropy or
anything and I would even highlight um
kind of on the next slide effectively
what it is doing is accepting that
you're not going to gain a lot of
resolution in these highly variable
regions and so you don't really have to
sample into those deeply because you've
accepted that it is variable it is not
something it is inherently variable in
the data we're not going to gain a a lot
of information from these regions um and
I it's highlighted in blue down there
and I think that's one of the big
highlight notes of this figure is
there's less Information Gain available
in these highly a variable regions and
that's something that makes this method
more robust and Powerful um when you're
dealing with some of these non uniform
variable
data yeah awesome and then the the
um street light effect is brought in
there so the avoidance of sampling in
ambiguous locations is sometime referred
to as a streetlight effect the tendency
to search where data are generated in a
minimally ambiguous way I.E under Street
Lamp compared to searching Elsewhere on
a darken street so I made some GPT 40
images some fun street light and on one
hand there's kind of this sense of like
is it constraining to look under only
the street light isn't that kind of
absurd and then there's the joke about
how what the person's looking for is
elsewhere but they're still searching
under the street light but they're
looking for something they they know is
elsewhere so that's the kind of tragic
element of it then there's this limited
element however there's also this
realistic element which is like well are
you supposed to search where you can't
sense or outside of where you are at
that moment so how could
you you know say that that wasn't just
and and then this paper is more framing
it as just a general condition of
perception like you're in your tactile
street light that is the part you can
see at
all you can have latent modeling of any
and other things but if it's not
grounded in some way to a measurement
made in a street light under the
metaphor where the light allows for
observation then you you're not
connected to data unless you're
connected to that street light so that's
just a very interesting kind of topic
and and reference that the authors use
what do you think absolutely I mean it
kind of boils down to you can't know
what you don't know or you can't observe
you know if you can only observe what's
underneath the street light then you
can't really know what else is outside
of there and so your inference
necessarily should be constrained to
what you are able to actually observe
you can't observe the unknown and so not
necessarily in this case um because you
don't even know if even exists that you
have no data to confirm or to refute
it all right section five Dynamic
processes so in that previous example
there was a data selection challenge
whether it was approached from the flat
fixed prior or all these other kind of
subsequent variants with the adaptivity
Andor with the cost now there's going to
be a time element brought into the
underlying generative model we'll just
go quickly here because that's the big
point they take the static distribution
that was sampled from and now give the
underlying process also variability
through time so this is like a very SPM
brain Laten State causal modeling type
set yeah anything you want to say on
that before we go in oh no go ahead okay
okay so they consider processes that
evolve in time equation 12 can be
interpreted similarly to equation 8 in
which the expectation of the data is
treated as a function approximation
which now includes a Time AR
so here was eight expectation of the
data given late and state
parameterization and policy equals so on
and then here there is data also being a
function of parameterization and policy
and then also bringing in an element
with a subscript tow for time uh then
you mentioned in your big questions the
different approaches that they raise
here with the three ways to bring
temporalities into a model so let's
definitely talk about that but just to
show their images seven and eight are
the pair for this dynamical section so
figure seven shows a graphical
representation of the matrices involved
in generating our data and the
inferences obtained after sampling so
here it is sampling from a Time variance
function and then figure eight goes into
more detail
and notes predictions based upon current
data can be used to inform predictions
about nearby spatial locations and to
predict and post dict the values of the
function at different points in time so
just like you could have a 2d plane
grayscale and infer the location of the
street light by pursuing like a gradient
up the light and then there would be
this optimal sampling like if you just
got one observation you would want to
sample on a line that was orthagonal
to the one that you couldn't resolve
lots of ways to think about this
sequential prediction but now the
underlying landscape also changes so
there's some temporal Dynamics and then
that can be fit with all these different
time series models and autocorrelation
and so on however that's specified
statistically in the generative model
but this section just shows however you
do make a statistical model for
time it's basically going to be the same
thing where
information is going to be drawn from a
distribution and now time is a variable
in that
distribution uh they right in this in
the previous section we have
demonstrated the way in which smarter
optimal sampling may be used to select
data in a manner that balances the cost
of sampling or performing further
experiments against the information
gained from those samples or experiments
each of these examples has relied upon
relatively simple and analytically
comfortable linear gussian systems next
we address active sampling in a
situation where analytical Solutions are
no longer possible so to highlight the
key formalisms that they're working with
in that kind of background
section uh or setup
section they kept one thing constant
which was that the the generative model
the generative process or however it's
considered with the family of equations
that the agent is inferring and tracking
hidden states with and that being the
same as the actual family of equations
that's generating the function of
observations and here that is relaxed so
that opens it up to all empirical
settings where you can just say right
off the bat we do not have access to the
generative model of those data so we're
making a map statistical map with all
the associated trade-offs and statuses
of like that genetic data or that trans
cryptomic data all those different kinds
of data sets starting from a position
where it's going to have to be
statistically
approximated and it isn't going to be
based unless explicitly otherwise on
actual knowledge about the causal
elements of the
system any any thoughts on that well in
something else that they noted in the
paper by adding this time element when
they're actually going through the time
series the model itself will will
preferentially select different data
beyond what it just recently selected so
time point one it selects X and Y data
time point two it might select l and m
data so it actually will go through and
select different types of data and it'll
take a little bit of time um what the
time is can be variable but it takes a
little bit of time before it revisits
some of that previous data um at a diff
at a previous time so by this you kind
of have a lighting window of data that
you're selecting over different time
periods yeah all right that's all going
to come to play in this clinical trial
which is the
big final contribution section of the
paper in our final example we
demonstrate the potential utility of the
ideas outlined above in the context of a
more concrete example so they model the
statistical setting here as an Adaptive
basian clinical intervention methodology
experiment for example the kind that was
done during the 2014 West African Ebola
outbreak the active sampling approach
advocated in this paper offers two main
opportunities to augment adaptive trial
designs first it allows us to adapt the
design to maximize the information we
obtain about treatment efficacy so
that's the pure sensemaking information
gained learning sampling from where it's
informative not from where like we
habitually or prefer to look and then
second to to balance and bring together
that information
gain with costs and that was brought in
with the cost of the sampling section
which was done in this paper by adding
the stop policy option which can be
probabilistically selected and then as
other sampling locations become less
informative or or if somebody was just
sampled and you know that there's a slow
Decay through time then on that subject
the stop policy cost would outweigh the
information gained from an
experiment and this is also I think will
be a very interesting discussion this
blows the line between clinical trial
and public health intervention and can
be seen as analogous to animal behavior
that is never fully exploitative or
explorative but is a balance between the
too so how do we think about that in
terms of biomedical and health security
and all these different topics and any
thoughts on this before we go into the
formalism of the clinical trial just
like about clinical trials or
anything yeah and I think that that's
going to be like that last point there
is going to be a big one going forward
of like how do you balance benefits to
the patient benefits to your trial
benefits to um essentially the company
like there's
a lot of different benefits and costs
that you have to weigh into this and so
these models are going to get very
complicated um when you start to distill
this into something especially with
health related um so it'll be very
interesting to see how this
evolves okay so here's how they do it
our setup is as follows for each new
cohort of participants we decide upon
the randomization ratio to adopt that's
the orange subscript R of policy so this
is policy on a randomization
ratio there's three options so this is a
discret but linearly ranked not fully
categorical policy decision where 1/2
would be the 50/50 sampling between the
two
groups whereas you know a priori that
sampling in a skewed ratio is going to
be
less informative like if you sampled
only from one you would obviously be
maximally uninformed about the other
however what's going to end up being
reflected in the policy decision to
shift to a 1/3 or a 2/3 which is
focusing observations on one branch of a
study more than the other is going to
focus on the explicit quantitative
preference for observations of survival
so that's going to be very interesting
to see see how the time variable which
relates to the experimental design but
by way of modeling the death curves of
the
participants and how different
preferences
for complimentary processes of reducing
uncertainty about the treatment specific
death curves and not preferring to see
death observations because that would
introduce the pragmatic imperative to
measure low survival experiments so
there's a lot of complexity in there
from the public health side also in this
very simple and interpretable way that
like this is like a basian light switch
with 50/50 information seeking mode or
tilt it one way or the other to bias
observations whereas if no information
had to be resolved then the policy
selection would Orient towards observing
long
survival whereas if that was somehow
changed then it would have to be
adaptively sampled on the Fly and
changing these ratios and all that what
do you what do you think about this yeah
and what we're gonna kind of get into is
um especially with these sorts of Health
decisions you want people to survive
like that's your that's your primary
goal in a lot of these you want to see
an effect you want to see a positive
effect of your treatment um one way or
the other you know if it's the placebo
that's the positive or it's the actual
treat treatment that's a positive you
want people to survive so this is kind
of getting into that ethics of making
sure that when you design these things
that you're doing the maximum good to
your participants um who you know may
not have you know much hope to sand on
um during some of these crises or
epidemics or whatever they are
experiencing at the time um so you want
to design this in such a way that you
know you keep them the patients in mind
that is the whole point of this and so
by having a basian kind
of preference and bias to keeping the
patient alive and the best outcome
you're maximizing how the patient's
outcome in the patient's
life thanks for adding that another
point to make this is from figure nine
that's going to come up but it really
highlights how sparse and few and
interpr able the basian graphical
formalism is and message passing which a
lot of the equations describe and the
discussion about RX and fur touched upon
message passing gives procedural ways to
implement this in computational systems
because it's sometimes hard to go from
the Simplicity of like this graphical
model to fitting it iteratively on
complex data sets but it's pretty clear
to see how different variables are up
stream or Downstream of other variables
and also how the
time uh
sampling can be shown to be which is
Upstream of data sampled as these other
factors are but it has a separable
interpretable calculable epistemic value
that doesn't have a certain kind of
connection to randomization ratio for
example so being able to have explicit
statistical calc calculations and
directedness is where the follow-up time
doesn't influence the treatment group
ratio or the randomization ratio or
other processes gives a type of
interpretability that the generative
model gives us the equations for and
then the pragmatic challenges are about
actually implementing that and then even
if the computational component were
totally addressed and abstracted away
that would basically Center these
broader questions
which I think the health examples are
great like jumping off
point4 yeah and uh you have probably
recalled from all the other different uh
figures despite how simple this figure
is the other figures the the plots were
very basic the models themselves like
you just had the three nodes you know
converging on the Y so despite how
simple this looks you are adding more
complexity to these um to these systems
and the more
complexity that you add the harder it is
the more computationally intensive it is
and so this is that question of how big
can you go you know how how many nodes
can you add how many parameters can you
add how much complexity can you add to
the system before it starts to break
down or not perform as well as you would
hope yeah so other than bringing in that
randomization ratio kind of expression
of
preference this model differs from the
prior one in that it's defined that the
kind of cognitive map is not the
territory they're different families so
that's what motivates this um
approximation approach so this is a
simple displacement where still it's a
trackable problem as they'll unfold
however the simulation family chosen for
the for like the approximation basically
the approximation could apply to any
data set but it might be woefully
inadequate like it might fit only one
component of it so that's Again part of
the interesting question is like how
similar does the statistical model have
to be or what information does it really
bring in and how to to model or work
with an empirical side um but just on a
more General statistical level uh
equations 156 17 describe some of the
technical details of the incremental
optimiz ation gradient scheme the Newton
optimization variational loss we'll talk
to Thomas at all figure N9 is displaying
the kind of before picture for the
randomized control trial so here's where
that graphical model is that was shown
earlier and then here are these two
groups and their survival through time
and different sampling uh choices that
are made
then just to to jump to figure
10 has the same layout as figure 9 but
now using the expected Information Gain
from equation 18 to guide sampling of
data so this is just to show the impact
of that active data sampling and then
we'll drop back to the equation uh there
are some notable differences between the
choices made in figure 10 compared with
9 choices
10 uh the most obvious of the
is that the followup times selected have
been moved later once optimal sampling
is
employed this makes intuitive sense as a
later follow-up time is informative
about the survival probabilities at all
prior times whereas an earlier follow-up
time is not informative about survival
probabilities at later
time
um where it gets in the final uh
simulation brings in the random sampling
plus the preference
element here's where the Symmetry is
broken to also want the measurement of
survival as more likely than death which
is how the preferences are specified in
active inference um and then the policy
switch is reflected in this like um part
where the observations are shifted later
because there's Le there's less than a
threshold of information to gain by
having them earlier and then they uh
even if there is equal variance I'm not
exactly sure we can ask between the two
branches there's uh an over sampling for
the group with a higher survival which
in this case was the placebo group so
anything to add on
this this this is the the like the Crux
of the whole making sure that you
optimize you know the patients's outcome
on this because the treatments and this
scenario were not um were not beneficial
they're actually harmful and so
throughout the course of the study this
by utilizing this model you actually
randomized more people into the placebo
group which caused a greater survival of
these uh individuals and so you're you
can already see the effect that this
sort of methodology has on clinical
trials because you're optimizing the
outcome and I think that is exactly what
you want to do in these Health decisions
in these trials in these things that
impact human health uh or Humanity in
general you want to optimize the outcome
uh and you know in this way you're
actually reducing the overall harm to
patients yeah interesting um here's the
specification for the information
gain so uh bringing in the
the form of the messages required for
equation three now with all these extra
components that have been added in with
the time variability demographic and the
sampling they write out some of the
technical details for the
approximations in the variational
lloss and then some aspects about those
models which we can ask about but figure
11 basically shows the big change which
is that uh as you go from having a a
flat sampling
distribution across time and across
treatment groups you can actually do
better than that basically by choosing a
sampling
regime that makes sense given the costs
of
sampling so that's just very interesting
because it it really does look like
given the the possibility for these two
lines to diverge their Divergence would
be largest later on whereas if you could
only schedule like one check for every
person if it was something that was
expected to happen later in life then
sampling all the young wouldn't even
make sense so then one approach is like
flat sampling but that is kind of
sometimes erroneously called uh like
unbiased or or uninformative but it is
very informative
and then this is pointing towards how
there can be better sampling than just
trying to go flat across the entire late
and state estimate if there are priors
relating to something they can be
leveraged as part of the probabilistic
sampling and adapted to the data set at
the in the end however for picking prior
families for the active data
selection that's a big question about
how how much it will change how the
algorithms work so I guess that kind of
takes us to the
uh
discussion the paper's Focus has been on
illustrating how we might make use of
information seeking objectives augmented
with costs which gave kind of the exit
Criterion or preferences which gives the
biased pragmatic part of data selection
to choose the best data to optimize our
inferences and they highlight that the
maximum entropy would yield identical
results in several of our examples so
that'll be interesting like what were
the examples where maximum entropy and
the Information Gain are
identical and then what are the real
world or the statistical settings when
the variance around predicted outcomes
is in
homogeneous how does the full cognitive
epistemic
modelbased objective
do differently than the max
ENT distribution dispersal kind of null
hypothesis any thoughts on
this I think you've captured it very
well okay um then there are several
technical points worth considering for
how we might Advance the concepts
reviewed in this paper so let's talk
about each of these one refinement of
the active selection process two
empirical eval ation of active versus
alternative sampling methods and three
identifying the appropriate cost
functions so we'll talk about those
coming up um conclusion here's the
entire
conclusion the key ideas involved in
appeal to fobal like sampling of small
portions of the total available data to
minimize computational cost that's a
very cool way to put it and it
highlights that kind of like sequential
scanning
but also opens up some very exciting
directions about how efficient that
could be for some but not other kinds of
problems and how those problems could be
identified or those patterns could be
filtered for to where different kinds of
cating models would be adaptive or not
so like these are all fun discussions
we'll have um and then they kind of
brought all the theoretical components
together at the end with the bay
adoptive clinical trial with the costs
of sampling uh constraints on sampling
and also the preference for survival
so what are your overall thoughts or
what are you excited about for the ones
to
come I'm excited to kind of see I mean
this is a fairly recent paper I'm
excited to see kind of where they have
gone since this paper was published you
know they had a number of kind of next
directions I would love to see what of
those dire
have they've taken what uh they've
compared it to other other sampling
techniques um this show shows a lot of
Promise going forward for very complex
and you know ethical uh situations or
situations where ethics are going to be
a huge component so kind of where that
is what they're going into and kind of
where they see you know further
improvements I still kind of want to
know what would happen
or what of these other time metrics um
or what other situations these time
metrics uh would or alternative time
models would be applicable to or if this
really is like the de facto just the way
it needs to be done totally totally fair
I think that could very well be the case
um I would just love to hear exactly you
if you did a hidden marov model how
would that look you know is is there a
benefit of that over the selection that
they have
um is there does it provide more or less
versatility in the models um these are
things that are going to be I think very
interesting going forward and then um
you know how do
we like like you noted in the discussion
how do you optimize those cost functions
what's what's a cost you know you're
dealing with clinical trials it's a
human life that's a cost time it's a
cost there's also just computer type how
much you can actually get um how much
compute you can get at any given moment
of time some of these uh machine
learning models that you might want to
apply this to are you know select data
going into um sometimes takes a long
time to train um how are you going to
sample data that's going into those
models how are you going to continually
feed those models appropriate data um
going forward so this is a huge broad
category of um directions that you can
go clinical trials was a a very
wonderful uh example of a complex
situation that is you know right there
applicable to human life um but then you
also have just data science in general
like how are you going to utilize this
to you know going more broad how you
going to utilize this just going forward
in any data sense data is growing it'll
continue to grow it will never really
stop growing so it's going to be more
and more important going forward to have
these methods more broadly
used and random nice random really
really good um but this holds a lot of
promise to
being and I would love to just hear
their thoughts on where that's going
where they see
that
yeah lot of lot of interesting
directions a few things that made me
think of one was about search and about
relational search Concepts page Rank and
everything syntactic semantic new kinds
of search algorithms and
personalization for search and learning
and updating and to what extent like
explicit cognitive modeling would change
the way that different recommendation
algorithms or different kinds of
um computer systems would work I I'll
read a question um and then any any
other questions otherwise this is our
our last slide so thank you Christopher
um okay Gia maximalist
wrote interesting point about biased and
unbiased sampling schemes perhaps this
points out the fact that unbiased
approaches are the wrong thing to strive
for in research study
design what do you think about that
unbiased research in study design um I
think there's a time in place for
unbiased and I think there's a time in
place for bias I think that but you when
you accept bias into your model or
refute take bias out of your um model
you need to understand why you're doing
that certain bias you don't want to have
you know researcher bias is something
that's a huge bias that you want to not
have for example um but in certain cases
um like in this paper where you actually
do want to have a bias um you want to
make an intelligent decision note while
you're making that decision call it out
and then build it into your model that
would be my
thought yeah that's interesting like
there are certain statistical
distributions the bias or the
constraints on which Define the research
study whereas other ones that can have
an explicitly strictly
negative like data loss or something but
then the tradeoffs of how that
distribution actually interacts with
others can enter into this more complex
experimental calculus that relates to
like well all these different
experimental factors and so the optimal
experiment for for
different Labs that or different moments
for the lab could look extremely
different and that's going to be the
case there's going to be dispersed
Behavior either way but then the
question is how is that actually driven
in a way that is doing better than
drawing from
distributions however even that does
interestingly well for the right
variables and you can mine bias all over
the place I bias in data design in
experiments is can be very useful
um so it'll just be interesting I think
it'll be Case by case is the way I see
it okay well do you have any last
comments uh I think that the main thing
here is I'm just very excited to see
this paper come out um I would love to
see how this is going to evolve over
time see if this can be uh applied to
different Technologies different areas
um I'm really excited just to see where
this is going because I think this is
just right on the cusp of what's
needed awesome thank you okay we will
look forward to it thank you see you all
right thanks
guys for